Guide to the West Indian Carnival Documentation Project records 2010.019
Brooklyn Historical Society
- Series 1: Oral Histories, 28 Gigabytes in 288 files
  - Pope, Kelvin, 1995 January 28; 2010.019.18
    In this interview Kelvin Pope discusses his calypso career, from its early start in the Calypso Monarch competitions in Trinidad to his projects as of 1995, the year of this interview. He reminisces about his participation in Carnival, as a mas (masquerade) player and as a musician. He provides a commentary on the evolution of calypso in the years preceding this interview and the emergence of technological advancements in mas costumes and music. Pope discusses the early years of the West Indian American Day Carnival, in Brooklyn and compares the contemporary Carnival to Carnival in Trinidad, Notting Hill and Toronto. He notes possible ways in which the Brooklyn Carnival could be made more accessible. Pope also suggests the need for education in handling the continuing conflict that the West Indian American Day Carnival Association has had with its Hasidic Jewish neighbors. Pope also suggests ways in which the association could partner with city government to ease the financial and structural burdens of the Carnival. Interview conducted by Michael Roberts.
    Brazil; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Ethnic identity; Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Social life and customs; Carnival; Carnival |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Eastern Parkway (New York, N.Y.); Grenada; London (England); Multiculturalism; Parades |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Race relations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Saint Vincent and the Grenadines; Trinidad; Trinidadian Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Social life and customs; Trinidadians |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Music; Pope, Kelvin; West Indian-American Day Carnival Association; West Indian American Day Carnival Parade (Brooklyn, N.Y.)
  - Quamina, Joyce, 1994 May 12; 2010.019.19
    Joyce Quamina was born in Port of Spain, Trinidad. In 1969, she immigrated to the United States and settled in Brooklyn, New York. A participant of Carnival in her native Trinidad, Quamina was a spectator of the original West Indian American parades in Harlem, New York and became an active participant when the parade began in Brooklyn, New York. In 1994, at the time of the interview, she was the business manager of the West Indian American Day Carnival Association (WIADCA). Quamina was the founder and organizer of the Carnival's Kiddies Carnival; an event in which children between the ages of infancy and sixteen participate in their own mas or masquerade parade. She was also a contributor to the Westchester County Caribbean Carnival, in White Plains, New York. After retiring from WIADCA, Quamina continued as a business consultant for the association.
    This is the first of two interviews with Joyce Quamina. The second interview was conducted on June 23, 1994. In this interview, Quamina discusses her childhood and adult experiences of Carnival in Trinidad. She relates memories of the West Indian Carnival in Harlem and provides a history of the Brooklyn West Indian American Day Carnival and its Kiddies Carnival, which she founded. She relates why the West Indian American Day Carnival is important to her. She also discusses what she views as the important factors of the Carnival's success. Quamina discusses the cultural diversity of the Carnival. Based on the popularity of the Carnival and the revenue it creates for the Crown Heights community and the City of New York, she sees a need for stronger sponsorship and media recognition beyond Brooklyn. The interview ends in a discussion of her role as business manager at the West Indian American Day Carnival Association. Interview conducted by Bill Pincheon.
    Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Ethnic identity; Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Social life and customs; Carnival; Carnival |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Eastern Parkway (New York, N.Y.); London (England); Miami (Fla.); Multiculturalism; Parades |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Race identity; Race relations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Trinidad; Trinidadian Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Social life and customs; Quamina, Joyce; West Indian-American Day Carnival Association; West Indian American Day Carnival Parade (Brooklyn, N.Y.)
  - Quamina, Joyce, 1994 June 23; 2010.019.20
    This is the second of two interviews with Joyce Quamina. The first interview was conducted on May 12, 1994. Here Quamina provides a more in depth discussion of her role as the West Indian American Day Carnival Association business manager. She discusses the process of registering vendors, acquiring information for the press and media outlets, and booking the performers for concerts conducted behind the Brooklyn Museum. Quamina relates her experiences initiating the Kiddies Carnival and the Junior Steel Band Panorama, noting the importance of each in ensuring the continuation of the Carnival and as a source for providing summer activities for community children. She provides an assessment of the future struggles of the Carnival, noting that obtaining consistent sponsorship will continue to be central to the Carnival's survival. Quamina discusses the history of the pan steel band in Trinidad and the United States, specifically addressing the role of girls and women. She also relates her opinions of the continuing cultural conflict between the Hasidic Jewish and West Indian communities of Crown Heights. Interview conducted by Bill Pincheon.
    Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Emigration and immigration; Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Ethnic identity; Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Social life and customs; Carnival |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Eastern Parkway (New York, N.Y.); Immigrants |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Jews |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Multiculturalism; Parades |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Race relations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Trinidadian Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Social life and customs; Quamina, Joyce; West Indian-American Day Carnival Association; West Indian American Day Carnival Parade (Brooklyn, N.Y.)
  - Reid, Michelle Quamina, 1994 July 19; 2010.019.21
    Michelle Quamina Reid was born in Trinidad. In 1970, she immigrated to Brooklyn, New York with her mother, Joyce Quamina. Reid had participated in the Carnival in Trinidad and, at the time of this interview in 1994, was a continual participant of the West Indian American Day Carnival parade, in Brooklyn. Her involvement included active membership in the West Indian American Day Carnival Association, where her mother Joyce was the business manager.
    In this interview Michelle Quamina Reid reminiscences about her participation in Carnival as a child in Trinidad and her experience of the West Indian American Carnival, in Harlem, New York. She discusses the origins of the West Indian American Day Carnival in Brooklyn; how her mother, Joyce Quamina, became involved in the West Indian American Day Carnival Association (WIADCA); and her own playing of mas. Reid was a judge for the Saturday event, the West Indian American Day Kiddies Carnival. She assisted her mother, Joyce Quamina, in registering vendors for Labor Day and in Be Aware of School, a program founded by Quamina to bring awareness to the importance of school and staying away from drugs. She provides an in-depth description of how the costumed bands of Carnival were judged. Reid contributes opinions on the importance of Carnival to the Caribbean heritage, the conflict that arose in 1994 with the religious Jewish community of Crown Heights, and how the different viewpoints of the next generation of WIADCA volunteers may affect the future of the Carnival. Interview conducted by Dwan Reece King.
    Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Ethnic identity; Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Social life and customs; Carnival |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Eastern Parkway (New York, N.Y.); Immigrants |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Jews |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Multiculturalism; Parades |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Race relations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Trinidadian Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Social life and customs; Reid, Michelle Quamina; West Indian-American Day Carnival Association; West Indian American Day Carnival Parade (Brooklyn, N.Y.)
  - Remy, Kwame, 1995 January 31; 2010.019.22
    Kwame Remy was born in Brooklyn, New York. Raised in the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn, he participated in the West Indian American Day Carnival festivities from the age of three; beginning with the Kiddie Carnival. In 1994, at the time of the interview, he was an eighteen year old senior at Sheepshead Bay High School. Remy was deeply involved in the mas competitions, winning prizes for elaborate costumes designed by Follette Eustace. He also worked for Joyce Quamina, the business manager for the West Indian American Day Carnival Association (WIADCA) in their administrative offices. Remy was involved in theater, music and dance. He went on to a career in music, as a vocalist in bands, and on cruise ships.
    In this interview Kwame Remy discusses his involvement in mas (masquerade) performance at Brooklyn's West Indian American Day Carnival. He explains the process of choosing a costume and theme for the mas and, in particular, his experiences with Follette Eustace, acclaimed designer. Remy expresses some of the frustrations of working in the office of the West Indian American Day Carnival Association and in the general organizing of the Carnival. He also notes the conflicts between the cultural communities of Crown Heights. Reflecting on the changes he has seen in his fifteen years of participation, he proposes changes he would like to see; including more local and citywide recognition. Of note are his opinions on the emergence of deejay music on the floats, the need for bands to respect the time restraints of the Carnival permits and the rising interracial participation at the event. Interview conducted by Dwan Reece King.
    Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Emigration and immigration; Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Economic conditions; Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Ethnic identity; Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Music; Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Social life and customs; Carnival |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Eastern Parkway (New York, N.Y.); Immigrants |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Multiculturalism; Race identity; Trinidad; Trinidadian Americans |z United States; Remy, Kwame; West Indian-American Day Carnival Association; West Indian American Day Carnival Parade (Brooklyn, N.Y.)
  - Rennie, Yvette, 1994 September 28; 2010.019.23
    Yvette Rennie was born in Manto, Morleytown, Trinidad and Tobago. In 1969, she immigrated to the United States to attend Howard University in Washington, D.C. In 1970, she traveled to New York, where she settled in Brooklyn and attended New York Community College. Rennie soon became involved in the West Indian Day Carnival festivities, where she played mas with Jab Jab performers. As of 1994, when the interview took place, she was an active participant in Carnival.
    In this interview Yvette Rennie discusses her immigration to the United States, the struggles of gaining a footing as an immigrant, and her early participation in the West Indian American Day Carnival. She defines the purpose of the Carnival and suggests that a wider knowledge of its history would relieve the community tensions the Carnival creates; this includes the lack of respect and recognition she feels the Carnival receives. She also explains Jab Jab, a masquerade form, and J'ouvert, the predawn precursor to the Carnival parade. Rennie notes the contributions of the Carnival participants to the character and economy of the city. She reflects on the police presence at the 1994 Carnival and the possibility of the New York City government subsidizing the event and becoming more involved in the Carnival's organization. The interview concludes with a discussion of what would improve the Carnival. Interview conducted by Michael Roberts.
    Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Ethnic identity; Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Social life and customs; Carnival; Carnival |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Eastern Parkway (New York, N.Y.); Immigrants |z New York (State) |z Kings County; London (England); Multiculturalism; Parades |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Police |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Trinidadian Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Social life and customs; Trinidadians |x Ethnic identity; Trinidadians |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Music; New York (N.Y.). Police Department; Rennie, Yvette; West Indian American Day Carnival Parade (Brooklyn, N.Y.)
  - Roberts, Michael, 1994 July 28; 2010.019.24
    Michael Roberts was born in St. George, on the island of Grenada. He immigrated to the United States in 1988, where he settled in the borough of Brooklyn. A journalist for most of his adult life, he was the managing editor of the Carib News at the time of this interview in 1994. He had held that position since 1990. He was a member of the West Indian-American Day Carnival Association.
    In this interview Michael Roberts describes his involvement in the West Indian American Day Carnival in Brooklyn; as a member of the press and as a member of the West Indian American Day Carnival Association (WIADCA). He addresses the lack of media attention the Carnival receives and notes the unrecognized political and economic power the Carnival signifies for the Caribbean community. Roberts also contributes his opinions concerning the cultural conflicts between the Caribbean and Hasidic communities of the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn, which hosts Carnival. Roberts describes Carnival in Grenada; providing a history of various facets and compares it to the Brooklyn manifestation. He reflects on the validation of Caribbean cultural identity that Carnival provides and notes its unifying qualities for the Caribbean and African American communities. He also discusses the racial disparity that hinders the Brooklyn Carnival from becoming as racially diverse as Caribbean Carnivals. The interview ends in a discussion of the need for a new generation of leadership for WIADCA and speculation on possible future changes to the parade. Interview conducted by Dwan Reece King.
    Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Ethnic identity; Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Social life and customs; Carnival; Carnival |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Eastern Parkway (New York, N.Y.); Grenada; Grenadian Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Social life and customs; Jews |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Multiculturalism; Race relations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Trinidadian Americans |z United States; Lezama, Carlos; Roberts, Michael; West Indian-American Day Carnival Association; West Indian American Day Carnival Parade (Brooklyn, N.Y.)
  - Seddio, Frank, 1994 September 29; 2010.019.25
    An Italian American, Frank Seddio was born in the Brooklyn neighborhood of Canarsie. A lifelong New York City civil servant, he has performed duties as a police officer, a community board chairman, State Assemblyman, district court judge, and as Chairman of the Kings County Democratic Party. Seddio was instrumental in the early phases of Brooklyn'sWest Indian American Day Carnival. From 1969-1970, as the community involvement liaison for the New York Police Department, he worked with Carlos Lezama in organizing the logistics of the parade. He later became a consultant for the West Indian American Day Carnival Association (WIADCA). When interviewed in 1994, Seddio was the Chairman of Community Board 18 in Brooklyn and the legal counsel of WIADCA.
    In this interview, Frank Seddio reflects on his early experiences and contributions to Brooklyn's Carnival. A former police officer, who worked on the civil logistics, of the Carnival, he describes the initial challenges of running it, including political and police department resistance to recognizing the Carnival as a community festival. He reflects on the necessity to constantly reassess and reformulate the event in its early phases and how it has continued to change during his twenty five years of involvement. He also describes the policies and training the Carnival's context required of New York police officers. The interview ends in a reflection of how his involvement in the Carnival has provided him a unique insight into the Caribbean community. He notes that it is necessary that the larger New York City community recognizes the contribution of the Caribbean community and the Carnival to the fabric of New York. Interview conducted by Maureen Mahon.
    Carnival; Carnival |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Social life and customs; Police |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Trinidadians |x Ethnic identity; Trinidadian Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Social life and customs; Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Ethnic identity; Trinidad; Trinidadians |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Music; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Canarsie (New York, N.Y.); Eastern Parkway (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn Museum; Lezama, Carlos; New York (N.Y.). Police Department; Seddio, Frank; West Indian-American Day Carnival Association; West Indian American Day Carnival Parade (Brooklyn, N.Y.)
  - Simpson, Charles, 1994 September 14; 2010.019.26
    Charles Simpson was born in Kingston, Jamaica. He has been a regular visitor to Trinidad and Tobago over the years where he has been actively involved in Carnival. He is the pioneer of Jamaica Carnival, which formed in 1990. A Brooklynite since 1970, Simpson was previously a soldier of the Jamaica Defense Force (JDF).
    Charles Simpson says in his interview that the West Indian American Day Carnival Association is doing a great job and that this is evidenced by the tremendous numbers who flock to Eastern Parkway every year at Labor Day to witness and participate in Brooklyn's Carnival. He sees problems of organization, but acknowledges that because of the size of the event this is inevitable. Simpson recalls his involvement in this Carnival over the years at various levels and it has been because of this collective experience that he became a key player in building the Jamaica Carnival, which takes place in April. He feels that city government can help more and he also thinks that the stature of the Carnival deserves better press, TV coverage, and input from the business sector by way of sponsorship. He argues that big business gets involved with the Macy's Parade and others of that kind, which in his view, cannot compare with the Labor Day Carnival Parade at any level. Interview conducted by Michael Roberts.
    Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Emigration and immigration; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) -- Social life and customs -- 20th century; Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Music; Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Social life and customs; Carnival; Carnival |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Eastern Parkway (New York, N.Y.); Immigrants |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Jamaica; Multiculturalism; Parades |z New York (State) |z New York; Trinidad; Simpson, Charles; West Indian-American Day Carnival Association; West Indian American Day Carnival Parade (Brooklyn, N.Y.)
  - Smith, Frank, 1994 July 21; 2010.019.27
    Frank Smith was born in Trinidad & Tobago. He immigrated to the United States in his thirties to care for his father, who was residing in Brooklyn. A calypso promoter, Smith was a participant of the West Indian American Day Carnival as an organizer and promoter of tents and the locations in which the calypsonians performed. At the time of this interview in 1994, Smith had recently closed his nightclub the Rainbow Terrace (1978-1993), which showcased calypso and American performers.
    In this interview Frank Smith recalls immigrating to the United States, his first impressions of Brooklyn, and his work as a promoter of calypso music for the West Indian American Day Carnival. Smith discusses changes he has seen in the Carnival, his attempts to coordinate a mas (masquerade) band, and his recruitment of talent for his calypso nightclub and the Carnival. He compares the Toronto Carnival, Caribana, to the Brooklyn Carnival, noting the differences and suggesting ways Brooklyn could better its participant route. Smith also discusses his use of mask and costumes from the Labor Day event to participate in the Fulton Street Festival. This event occurred approximately two weeks after the West Indian American Day Carnival. Interview conducted by Dwan Reece King.
    Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Emigration and immigration; Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Economic conditions; Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Ethnic identity; Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Music; Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Social life and customs; Carnival; Carnival |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Eastern Parkway (New York, N.Y.); Parades |z New York (State) |z New York; Toronto (Ont.); Trinidad; Trinidadian Americans |z United States; Smith, Frank; West Indian American Day Carnival Parade (Brooklyn, N.Y.)
  - Stanislaus, Lamuel, 1994 August 4; 2010.019.28
    Dr. Lamuel Stanislaus was born in Grenada. He immigrated to the United States in 1945 to attend Howard University, where he subsequently received a medical degree in dentistry. After receiving his degree, he moved to Brooklyn where he maintained a dental practice for forty-three years. A founding member of the West Indian American Day Carnival Association, Dr. Stanislaus was also the United Nations Ambassador to Grenada from 1985-1990. At the time of this interview in 1994, he had recently retired his practice.
    In this interview Dr. Lamuel Stanislaus describes his personal life and relates the history of the Lenten Carnival in its European and African roots. He describes his initial impression of the West Indian American Day festivities in Harlem, New York in the 1940s and the events leading to the inception of the West Indian American Day Carnival and its parent association in Brooklyn. Dr. Stanislaus discusses the planning process of the Carnival. In 1994, the Carnival coincided with the Jewish holiday of Rosh Hashanah. This created a conflict between Carnival organizers and members of the Hasidic Jewish community of Crown Heights in Brooklyn. Dr. Stanislaus provides his opinion on this situation and that of the Crown Heights riot of 1991. He speculates on the potential political influence the Carnival raises and discusses how the event can be used to support charities in the community and around the world. Interview conducted by Dwan Reece King.